<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article>
<article
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >
  <info>
    <title>Predicting body mass in bipedal dinosaurs</title>
  </info>
  <para>
    ##::: {style=<quote>text-align: justify</quote>}
  </para>
  <section xml:id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Body mass (BM) is one of the most significant variables in the
      biology of an organism. It could provide insights into their
      physiology, ecology, or behavior. Indeed, it could influence
      speciation and extinction rates; driving patterns such as giantism
      in some vertebrates like dinosaurs, whales, and palaeognathaes.
      However, while obtaining BM data from extant species is relatively
      straightforward, it becomes challenging when attempting to obtain
      this variable for extinct organisms. Therefore, prediction becomes
      the only viable method to obtain this feature.
    </para>
    <para>
      Various methods exist to reconstruct body size, shape, and weight
      from preserved skeletons (Fossils). The most popular approaches
      are volumetric density (VD) and extant scaling (ES). Although VD
      was the initial proposal for calculating BM, ES is currently the
      most widely used tool. It is based on linear models, is easy to
      replicate and use, and is more cost-effective compared to the
      scans used by VD. However, current models have faced criticism due
      to their potential to over- or under-estimate BM. Another
      challenge arises from the distinct distribution of mass in
      quadrupeds compared to bipeds, leading to more complexities in
      calculating the BM of bipeds as predictors need to be restricted
      only to forelimbs. Furthermore, the wide range of BM distribution
      in modern birds, ranging from 50g to 130,000g, presents an
      additional challenge, especially when the presence of giantism in
      the Palaeognatha group is considered as an outlier in the
      distribution.
    </para>
    <para>
      To address the biped issue, some researchers have proposed models
      that exclusively utilize modern birds (excluding Palaeognathes),
      incorporate humans, or eliminate the humerus as a covariant.
      However, no attempts have been made to fit a model using different
      datasets, including Palaeognathes as an essential part of the
      sample. Re-evaluating the proposed models is thus warranted,
      considering that this group could serve as a good proxy for the BM
      of dinosaurs.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="materials-and-methods">
    <title>Materials and Methods</title>
    <section xml:id="preliminary-therapoda-data-set">
      <title>Preliminary Therapoda data set</title>
      <para>
        In order to get the preliminary database, I joined observations
        from Theropoda group, that had avalibale variables such as body
        mass (BM.g), femur circumference (FemurCirc) and femur length
        (FemurLen). I gathered those dataset from different sources that
        have used them mainly for fitting models to predict body mass in
        non-avian dinosaurs or for evaluating evolutionary and
        ecological questions. Despite of my aim involved only the three
        variable named above, I included extra information as sex,
        estimation type, pneumatic feature among other, for future
        researching.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="preliminary-palaeognathae-dataset">
      <title>Preliminary Palaeognathae dataset</title>
      <para>
        To include the largest and heaviest living birds in to the the
        sample, I gathered every published paper with available body
        mass, and femur circumference or femur length from Palaeognathae
        group. Most of those observations have been obtained from alive
        animals, getting only femur length instead of femur
        circumference measure, given that it is only available from
        specimens in museums.
      </para>
      <para>
        Considering this issue, to collect a workable database, I
        decided to split the experimental design in three different
        analysis (see <link linkend="fig-expDesign">Figure 1</link>).
        Thus, to use Palaeognathae observations to fit models and then
        to predict body mass, I had first to predict femur circumference
        from femur length (see
        <link linkend="fig-expDesign">Figure 1</link> A), followed by
        the main analyses (see
        <link linkend="fig-expDesign">Figure 1</link> B and C)
      </para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="Biol607_files/pics/experimentalDesign2.png" id="fig-expDesign" role="margin-caption" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Figure 1: Experimental design</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="preliminary-modeling-analysis-predicting-femur-circumference">
      <title>Preliminary modeling analysis: Predicting Femur
      circumference</title>
      <para>
        First off, from preliminary Therapoda and Palaeognathae
        databases, I filter the observations with femur circumference
        and length belonging to Class Aves (Crow-group in Therapoda). I
        explored the relationship between both variables femur
        circumference and femur length. Then, I decided to fit nine
        different models including or not low taxonomic levels
        (infraclass and order levels) as a categorical co-variant. To
        get the best model that fitted to my data, I did two parallel
        analyses (<link linkend="fig-expDesign">Figure 1</link> A) . For
        the first one I split the Aves data set in two subsets (training
        and test). For the training sunset I fit the 9 models (
        <link linkend="tbl-cap-marging-tab4">Table 4</link> ) and then
        use the coefficients to predict the test subset. I compared the
        real values with the predicted and used Mean Standard Error as
        model performance measure and AIC as best-model selector. For
        the second subset, I kept the whole subset and fitted the nine
        models using re-sampling K-folds Cross Validation approach. I
        used 10 folds and 20 re-sampling iterations. In this case I used
        Root Mean Standard Error as the measure to evaluate model
        performance and selection.
      </para>
      <para>
        With the best model I predicted femur circumference from femur
        length for the Palaeognathae database. I joined both
        preliminaries databases to make a main database to continue with
        the main analyses (
        <link linkend="fig-expDesign">Figure 1</link> A and B ).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="fitting-model-to-predict-body-mass">
      <title>Fitting model to predict body mass</title>
      <para>
        Using the final set data, y explore la relacion de ambas
        variables body mass y circunferencia. al igual que el analsis
        preliminar, realice dos analisis en paralelo. En el primero,
        dividi el set de datos en dos, y fije 6 modelos distintos al set
        de entrenamiento, usando estos modelos evalue la predicion de
        ellos usando el set de test. En ambos subsets medi el error como
        RMSE y el AIC como medida de selection. En el segundo caso,
        mantuve el 100% de los conjunto de datos y fije los mismos m6
        moleos usando leave-out-one cross validation. RMSE fue la
        metrica de error, para finalmente seleccionar el mejor modelo de
        prediccion de body mass.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="comparando-modelos">
      <title>Comparando modelos</title>
      <para>
        Para evaluar cuan bien este nuevo modelo predice el body mass,
        yo compare su performance con respecto a los modelos publicados
        previamente (citas). 4 modelos en total fueron contrastado con
        el escogido en este estdio.Para ello, seleccione un set de datos
        de dinosaurios teropods (xx sp XX ordenes XXX obser) y una
        muestra de 28 obsercinones del set de datos de paleognata. De
        esta manera, podria comparar el performece de predicion de todos
        los modelos, no solo dentro de dinosaurios, sino dentro de crow
        group de aves.
      </para>
      <para>
        Datos que los datos retro transformado presentan dificultades al
        calcular intervalos de confianza y de prediccion, segui las
        recomendacione sde XXX y use MPPE como metrica de error y
        comparacion entre modelos.
      </para>
      <para>
        Para el analisis entero yo fije la semilla en 999
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="results">
    <title>Results</title>
    <para>
      Preliminar dataset included 1465 samples, which corresponded to
      non-avian therapods, stem group and crow group of Aves.
    </para>
    <anchor xml:id="tbl-cap-marging-tab1" />
    <table>
      <title>Table 1: MPG vs horsepower, colored by
      transmission.</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              orders
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Species
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Obs
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              39
            </entry>
            <entry>
              589
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1465
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>
      Preliminar dataset in Palaeognatha included 1115 sample that has
      information about Femur lenght but not about Femur Circumference.
    </para>
    <anchor xml:id="tbl-cap-marging-tab2" />
    <table>
      <title>Table 2: MPG vs horsepower, colored by
      transmission.</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              orders
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Species
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Obs
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              7
            </entry>
            <entry>
              38
            </entry>
            <entry>
              115
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>
      Thus, the data set for predicting femur circumference included
      only observations fro the crown group. 1172 Observations for 32
      orders and 502 species
    </para>
    <anchor xml:id="tbl-cap-marging-tab3" />
    <table>
      <title>Table 3: MPG vs horsepower, colored by
      transmission.</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              orders
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Species
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Obs
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              32
            </entry>
            <entry>
              502
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1172
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Final_analysis_files/figure-docbook/fig-cap-margin-plot1-1.png" id="fig-cap-margin-plot1" role="margin-caption" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Figure 2: MPG vs horsepower, colored by transmission.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      Following XXXX, linearity between both variables is a conserved
      feature in low taxonomic levels such as like Sauropoda, Therapoda
      and Ornithischia.
    </para>
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Final_analysis_files/figure-docbook/fig-cap-margin-plot2-1.png" id="fig-cap-margin-plot2" role="margin-caption" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Figure 3: MPG vs horsepower, colored by transmission.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
    <anchor xml:id="tbl-cap-marging-tab4" />
    <table>
      <title>Table 4: MPG vs horsepower, colored by
      transmission.</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Models
            </entry>
            <entry>
              df
            </entry>
            <entry>
              AIC
            </entry>
            <entry>
              adjR2
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_FL
            </entry>
            <entry>
              3
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5793.0242
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9258922
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              logFC_logFL
            </entry>
            <entry>
              3
            </entry>
            <entry>
              -554.3573
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9661845
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_FL.Clade1
            </entry>
            <entry>
              4
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5786.0322
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9267005
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              logFC_logFL.Clade1
            </entry>
            <entry>
              4
            </entry>
            <entry>
              -587.0077
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9675837
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_poly2FL
            </entry>
            <entry>
              4
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5049.1914
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9701565
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_poly2FL.Clade1
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5051.1380
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9701584
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_poly3FL
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5050.9238
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9701662
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_poly3FL.Clade1
            </entry>
            <entry>
              6
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5052.9117
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9701666
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_FL.Clade2
            </entry>
            <entry>
              34
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5353.2854
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9598090
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              logFC_logFL.Clade2
            </entry>
            <entry>
              34
            </entry>
            <entry>
              -1138.5410
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9846227
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_poly2FL.Clade2
            </entry>
            <entry>
              35
            </entry>
            <entry>
              4718.8069
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9815059
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              FC_poly3FL.Clade2
            </entry>
            <entry>
              36
            </entry>
            <entry>
              4708.8941
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.9817727
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <anchor xml:id="tbl-cap-marging-tab5" />
    <table>
      <title>Table 5: MPG vs horsepower, colored by
      transmission.</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              orders
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Species
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Obs
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              27
            </entry>
            <entry>
              446
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1036
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Final_analysis_files/figure-docbook/fig-cap-margin-plot3-1.png" id="fig-cap-margin-plot3" role="margin-caption" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Figure 4: MPG vs horsepower, colored by transmission.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Final_analysis_files/figure-docbook/unnamed-chunk-15-1.png" role="margin-caption" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>MPG vs horsepower, colored by transmission.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
    <anchor xml:id="tbl-cap-marging-tab6" />
    <table>
      <title>Table 6: MPG vs horsepower, colored by
      transmission.</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Models
            </entry>
            <entry>
              DF
            </entry>
            <entry>
              AIC
            </entry>
            <entry>
              adjR2
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              BM_FC
            </entry>
            <entry>
              3
            </entry>
            <entry>
              16393.9376001463
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.664245607357889
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              logBM_logFC
            </entry>
            <entry>
              3
            </entry>
            <entry>
              808.313403286504
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.955983623367339
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              BM_poly2FC
            </entry>
            <entry>
              4
            </entry>
            <entry>
              14432.4220187293
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.96865720899441
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              BM_poly3FC
            </entry>
            <entry>
              5
            </entry>
            <entry>
              14425.6720054266
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.968986684648113
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              BM_spline1
            </entry>
            <entry>
              9
            </entry>
            <entry>
              14391.0827181163
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.96892674034371
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              BM_spline2
            </entry>
            <entry>
              10
            </entry>
            <entry>
              14395.8463345584
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.969138221363873
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              BM_spline3
            </entry>
            <entry>
              10
            </entry>
            <entry>
              14395.8463345584
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.969611722714325
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="eval-models">
    <title>Eval models</title>
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Final_analysis_files/figure-docbook/fig-cap-margin-plot7-1.png" id="fig-cap-margin-plot7" role="margin-caption" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Figure 5: MPG vs horsepower, colored by transmission.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Final_analysis_files/figure-docbook/fig-cap-margin-plot8-1.png" id="fig-cap-margin-plot8" role="margin-caption" />
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Figure 6: MPG vs horsepower, colored by transmission.</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
      #:::
    </para>
  </section>
</article>
